<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-12T14:20:06+00:00</updated><id>https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/feed.xml</id><title type="html">WCU-AIR</title><subtitle>The Artificial Intelligence Research (AIR) Lab at West Chester University is a collaborative community of faculty and students exploring how AI can make a positive impact. We bring together diverse computer science, engineering, and education perspectives, with a strong emphasis on mentorship and hands-on experience. Our members contribute to publications, open-source projects, and applied collaborations while developing skills that prepare them for both academic and industry careers. By fostering inclusion and curiosity, the AIR Lab provides an environment where innovation and learning thrive side by side.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">SURF Award Recipients</title><link href="https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/2025/11/12/surf-awards.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SURF Award Recipients" /><published>2025-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-12T14:18:30+00:00</updated><id>https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/2025/11/12/surf-awards</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/2025/11/12/surf-awards.html"><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations to Kadin Matotek and Huy Nguyen for receiving the WCU-Student Undergraduate Research Foundation (SURF) Spring 2026 Awards!</p>

<p>Kadin’s project seeks to extend his prior award-winning research on evaluating the problem-solving limitations of locally hosted Large Language Models (LLMs). He aims to perform a comprehensive, multi-model analysis of code generation reliability across diverse architectures and scales. Through the Spring 2026 semester, Kadin will conduct controlled experiments using an enhanced offline evaluation pipeline. The study will expand from the initial eight open-source models to more than fifty, spanning sizes from small (0.5B) to mid-scale (14B) parameters. Each model will be benchmarked across datasets including HumanEval, MBPP+, CodeContests, and custom-curated Kattis and LeetCode corpora.</p>

<p>Huy’s project focuses on analyzing, understanding, and modifying the Real-Time Transport Protocol (RTP) to enhance its security and user access management features. Students will investigate the protocol structure, identify unused header spaces, and embed additional security-related information without adding overhead. The project also aims to improve performance by refining or removing low-priority steps. Testing will be conducted using real network data, and results will be shared for collaborative evaluation.</p>]]></content><author><name>Linh B. Ngo</name></author><category term="accomplishments" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Congratulations to Kadin Matotek and Huy Nguyen for receiving the WCU-Student Undergraduate Research Foundation (SURF) Spring 2026 Awards!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/images/logo-dark.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/images/logo-dark.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">AIR Lab at CCSC-E</title><link href="https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/2025/10/25/ccsce.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AIR Lab at CCSC-E" /><published>2025-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-12T14:18:30+00:00</updated><id>https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/2025/10/25/ccsce</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/2025/10/25/ccsce.html"><![CDATA[<p>This weekend, the AIR Lab participated at the Consortium of Computing Sciences in Colleges - Eastern’s 41st Annual Conference Region this weekend.</p>

<p>In the Capture the Flag security competition, Benjamin Crocker and Huy Nguyen are part of the WCUL8R Cybersecurity team that won First Place at the Capture-the-Flag security competition.</p>

<p>In the Poster session, Chrisma Ndlovu presented his early results titled “Prompt-Driven AI Feedback for Introductory CS Course”. The poster won Best Student Poster Award.</p>

<p>In the Paper session, we have two papers peer-reviewed and accepted: “Evaluating the Limitations of Local LLMs in Solving Complex Programming Challenges” with Kadin Matotek as first author and Heather Cassel as second author, and “A Detailed Comparative Analysis of Blockchain Consensus Mechanisms” with Kaeli Andrews as first author. All students are first-time presenters at academic conferences. Kadin and Heather’s paper won Best Research Paper Award.</p>

<p>For the Programming Competition, Team ByteMe (Benjamin Crocker, Alexander Pham, and Huy Nguyen), won second place in the competition.</p>]]></content><author><name>john-doe</name></author><category term="conference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This weekend, the AIR Lab participated at the Consortium of Computing Sciences in Colleges - Eastern’s 41st Annual Conference Region this weekend.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/images/2025/ccsce/ccsce.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://wcu-air.github.io/airlab/images/2025/ccsce/ccsce.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>